<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at St. Marys Church in Cambridge, January the 6th being the feast of the Epiphany / by Francis Hare ...</title>
            <author>Hare, Francis, 1671-1740.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15305623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15305623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1189:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at St. Marys Church in Cambridge, January the 6th being the feast of the Epiphany / by Francis Hare ...</title>
                  <author>Hare, Francis, 1671-1740.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the university press for Edmund Jeffery ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge [Cambridgeshire] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title page reads: Mr. Hare's sermon on the Epiphany.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Epiphany --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103395:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON <hi>Preach'd at S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi>
               </hi> MARYS <hi>Church</hi> IN CAMBRIDGE, JANUARY the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Being the FEAST OF THE <hi>EPIPHANY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>FRANCIS HARE,</hi> A.M. and Fellow of KING'S College.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed at the <hi>Univerſity Preſs,</hi> for <hi>Edmund Jeffery,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:103395:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103395:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hare</hi>'s SERMON On the <hi>EPIPHANY.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:103395:3"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>THO. GREENE, Procan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>HUMF. GOWER, Prof.</hi> Marg.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>S. BLITHE,</hi> Aul. Clar. Cuſtos.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>C. RODERICK,</hi> Coll. Regal. <hi>Praep.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103395:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LUKE II. xxxii.</bibl>
               <q>A Light to lighten the Gentiles—</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Hymn from whence theſe Words are taken, is ſo well known by being made a part of the conſtant Service of the Church, that I need not mention either the Author or Occaſion of them; Every body knows When they were ſpoken and by Whom, ſees Who it is they point to, and is before-hand with me in the application of them to the Day; Which the Church hath ſet apart to commemorate that great Myſtery, the Manifeſtation of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to the Gentiles, a Myſtery hid from Ages and Generations, but now made known in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Wiſe Men; who by the Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Star came from the Eaſt to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to pay their homage to the New-born King: For they were the Firſt-fruits of the Gentiles; in Them was this Manifeſtation, not only ſignified and ſhadowed forth, but actually begun; ſo ſoon did the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Glory of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> begin to be a Light to the Gentiles alſo.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103395:4"/>
            <p>This is a Day much to be remembred in it ſelf; and as 'tis the laſt of the Solemnity of this Seaſon, ſo is it the great Reaſon we remembred thoſe that went before it: For what if <hi>Chriſt</hi> were in the fulneſs of Time Born of a pure Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, what if he were Circumciſed the Eight day, and made obedient to the Law; what had theſe things been to us, or what Intereſt had we had in them, if He that was Born and Circumciſed, had not been Manifeſted to us?</p>
            <p>If we have any Senſe of the Miſery the Gentile World had hitherto, and would have ſtill continued to lie under, if the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> had not been reveal'd at all; and the yet greater Evils they muſt have undergone, if he had been reveal'd in the manner the <hi>Jews</hi> expected; we ſhall ſee abundant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to celebrate this Day, and joyfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Goodneſs of God to us, in that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of His Son, which we now comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate. And if a Senſe of being deliver'd from our Miſery, if a Senſe of having the greateſt Evils remov'd far from us, be ſufficient to excite Joy and Praiſe, and Thankſgiving in us; much more will our Rejoycing be increas'd, much greater will our Obligations be, when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Favours and Bleſſings we do or may enjoy, if it be not our own Fault, in the room of thoſe Evils, which we muſt have been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expoſed to.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103395:4"/>
            <p>If the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> had not been revealed at all, the World would ſtill have lain in Sin, in Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and great Darkneſs, and had neither known God, nor been known by Him; they would have been ſtill wandring after their own Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and either not ſearched, or ſearch'd in vain for any real Happineſs; their Wiſdom muſt ſtill have ended in extreme Folly, and they at laſt forc'd to ſit down, after having tired themſelves in endleſs Mazes and Uncertainties, in profound Darkneſs, and in the Shadow of Death. Such would have been the wretched State of Man, had the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> never come, or which is all one, had never been revealed to us; for ſuch it was before He came, as I ſhall ſhew more at large by and by, and ſuch it ſtill is in thoſe parts of the Gentile World, where the Light of the Goſpel has never Shone.</p>
            <p>But Worſe, much Worſe had our Condition been, if the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> had been revealed in the manner the <hi>Jews</hi> expected; then indeed He had been a Light to the Gentiles, but not to Lighten and Comfort, and give Life to; far from that, He would have been a Light Dreadful and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, to Burn up and to Deſtroy the Nations of the Earth, as many as would not bow their Neck to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Yoke; which was now, in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Time to be laid on all People, and be, as they thought, Univerſally Submitted to: for they expected the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhould be a Mighty Deliverer, a Glorious Conquerour, One that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103395:5"/> ſhould lift up his Voice on High, that ſhould be Dreadful to the Kings of the Earth, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all People to Himſelf. They expected a <hi>Star ſhould ariſe out of Jacob, and a Sceptre out of Judah, that ſhould ſmite the Corners of Moab, and deſtroy all the Children of Seth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the Expectations of the <hi>Jews;</hi> which had they been fulfilled, had the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> appeared, as they flattered themſelves He would; they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed would have had great Reaſon to Rejoyce: for to ſee the Slavery they were under, for in truth their Subjection to the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke was little better, to ſee that not only changed into a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Liberty, but to have themſelves the Power of the World in their own Hands; to ſee all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Kingdoms fall down before them; but above all, to have it now their turn to Rule over thoſe, who at preſent Ruled it over them; this would have been matter of great Joy to any People, tho' they had been more Conſiderable, had Suffered leſs, and had had a better Temper than the <hi>Jews.</hi> But how great ſoever their Joy would have been on this Occaſion, the reſt of the World would have had little Reaſon to join with them; their Portion would have been to Lament themſelves and their hard Fortune, their Sorrow would have riſe with the Calamities this State of Things would have reduced them to, and both would have increaſed in proportion to the Proſperity and Joy of this little People;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103395:5"/> who confined to a narrow Corner of the World, now made no Figure, were no Terrour to their Neighbours, but lived to themſelves, Deſpiſing and Deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>But, Thanks be to God, this is not the Caſe; their Expectations are ſo far from being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, that the exact Reverſe of them is come to paſs. They are ſo far from being the only People whom the Lord hath Redeemed, ſo far from engroſſing the Bleſſings of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to themſelves, that they are almoſt the only Nation that has had no part in them: For <hi>God hath given them the Spirit of Slumber, Eyes that they ſhould not ſee, and Ears that they ſhould not hear:</hi> They ſtumbled, they fell, and <hi>thro' their fall Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is come unto the Gentiles.</hi> So great is <hi>the Goodneſs and Severity of God; on them which fell, Severity; but Goodneſs towards us.</hi> His Severity indeed is by no means matter of Joy to a Good Man; far be thoſe Thoughts from us, we ought rather to pity their great Unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and pray for the Time when God will have Mercy on his Ancient People; but we ought to make this Uſe of it, it ſhould teach us to ſet a greater value on his Goodneſs, who have received ſuch undeſerved and unexpected Favours from Him, <hi>When we were no People, when we ſought Him not, nor asked after Him;</hi> and that not in common and together with them who were His People, and whoſe God He had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103395:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> declared Himſelf to be; but what is much more ſurprizing, they had no Share in them; <hi>The caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them away was the Reconciling of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we may the better underſtand the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Mercy, and have a due Senſe of the Obligations it brings with it, I ſhall conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> the State of the Gentile World before our Saviour came;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Next</hi> wherein the Enlightning it conſiſted; and</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Laſt</hi> place make ſome Application of the Whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To conſider the State of the Gentile World before our Saviour came, we find it fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently repreſented to us in the Scriptures un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one Word, and that is Darkneſs; <hi>To give Light to them that ſit in Darkneſs; Ye were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Darkneſs; but now are ye Light in the Lord; who hath called you out of Darkneſs, into mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Light; We are not of the Night, nor of Darkneſs; Who hath delivered us from the power of Darkneſs;</hi> with many more places of the like nature, in all which the Word <hi>Darkneſs</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d to repreſent the Sad Condition the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rld was in, before the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to them: Sad indeed it was, if this be a juſt Name for it; For Darkneſs we ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103395:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> great and natural Averſion to, 'tis a State of Inactivity, deprives us of all the Uſe and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Day, and is utterly unfit for Motion; we either cannot move, or cannot be ſure we move aright; 'tis a time fit only for the Beaſts and Men of Prey to move in; for we want the Benefit of the Nobleſt and moſt Uſeful Senſe we have, our Sight; without which the Reſt are of very little Uſe, either to keep us from the Dangers which we ſhould otherwiſe bring upon our ſelves, or to defend us from the Inſults and Injuries of others. In a word, there is nothing creates a greater, or more univerſal Fear, than long or unuſual Darkneſs; and nothing but Cuſtom, and the help of Artificial Light, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles us to what is uſual. What then can a State of Darkneſs mean leſs than a Wretched, Ignorant, Uncomfortable State; a State full of Confuſion and Error, of Corrupt Opinions, and Abominable Practices; a State Hideous and Ugly as the firſt Chaos, when the Earth was <hi>without Form and Void; and Darkneſs was upon the Face of the Deep?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that the State of the Gentile World before our Saviour came, was a State of Darkneſs, and deſervedly 'called by ſo Black a Name, muſt be owned by all who have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver look't into theſe Times, and conſidered the Particulars wherein this Darkneſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; which, were they all put together, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103395:7"/> give us a juſt Conception of that Univerſal Night, which was then ſpread over the Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual World. The great Ignorance they were under, and the Conſequences of it, would give us ſuch a frightful Scene of things, as one can hardly tell how to Believe; or Believing, how to Reconcile it with the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of that Being, whoſe Eyes are always upon the Works of his hands, and who <hi>from the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Ruleth over All.</hi> The firſt and great Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Error they were in, was concerning the True GOD; their Notions were ſo contrary and inconſiſtent upon this Head, that one can't read them without deeply and frequently Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting, how Poor and Low a Thing the Mind of Man is, when he Attempts to comprehend Divine Truths. The World was divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two Extremes; they were either for many Gods, or none at all; Opinions almoſt as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from Truth, as from one another. The Oldeſt indeed, and always moſt Univerſal Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and which perhaps aroſe from the Scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and Corrupt Remains of ſome Ancient and Genuine Traditions, was that of many Gods: But this was ſo abſurd in it ſelf, and all it's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences; their Number, Names, Actions, Offices, Worſhip and Sacrifices, were ſo very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable, ſo impoſſible to be made Senſe of; that when the World grew more refined, the Men of Penetration and Thought, to mend the matter, betook themſelves to the oppoſite Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103395:7"/> and becauſe they could no where meet with a Rational Religion, vainly concluded that Reaſon and Religion were in their Natures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent; they concluded no Religion could be True, becauſe all they had ſeen were certainly Falſe. For they were in almoſt every Country different at the ſame time, and in the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try at different times: they worſhipped they knew not what nor why, they worſhipped Stocks and Stones, and under them Imaginary Beings infinitely above Humane Nature, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with others as much below it.</p>
            <p>We have an Epitome of the groſſeſt and fouleſt Superſtition the World ever knew, in that one People the <hi>Egyptians:</hi> Nothing can be more ridiculous, than what the beſt Writers tell us of their Gods, and their Religious Rites; and in their Story we ſee in effect the Religions of other Nations. For <hi>Egypt</hi> was the great Nurſery of Superſtition; from thence aroſe that thick Darkneſs, which afterwards overſpread the Earth; not that this Darkneſs was every where uniformly ſpread; as ſoon as it began to be diffus'd, 'twas divided and broke into une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts, inſenſibly altered as it went along, and received different Additions, according to the ſeveral Climates to which it came. By which means their Religions by degrees differed more from one another, but not leſs from Reaſon than before. Sacred and Prophane were every
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103395:8"/>where arbitrary things, and ſometimes names directly oppoſite were given to the ſame thing by different Orders of Men in the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. There was nothing ſo abſurd which Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition could not lead them into a Belief of; and if one may judge of what they thought by what they did, one would think, the more abſurd a thing was, the more they liked it: otherwiſe one can't imagine how the World could have fall'n into ſo great a variety of Errors, ſo very groſs, with ſo ſmall a mixture of Truth in them; which, as it was very little, ſo very probably 'twas ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to any right Reaſoning; for had they reaſoned about theſe things rightly, they muſt needs have found out more Truth, they could not have ſtopped ſo very ſhort, and have taken up with ſo few right Notions, ſo extremely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed with falſe ones. Theſe therefore 'tis likely were borrowed from ſome Traditions, which once were more perfect, but now were grown very old, and by length of time, and frequent Tranſplanting ſo altered and defaced, that the firſt Authors of them would ſcarce have known them; ſo little of the Genuine parts remained, and the old Strokes were in a manner all gone. Elſe how could things ſo incoherent be embraced, as there was in moſt of their Religions? how was it poſſible ſo many and ſo different Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions could be deductions from the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principles?</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:103395:8"/>
            <p>'Tis hard to conceive how the Opinions of any one People, taken together, could proceed from any Principles at all: nor indeed did they; theſe Religions were then form'd when the World were children in Underſtanding; when they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired every thing, and underſtood nothing; nothing of Arts and Sciences, nothing of the Cauſes and Natures of things, in a word, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beyond their Senſes, and what was juſt before their Eyes; and by that means became an eaſie Prey to a few, who thought farther than the reſt, and uſed them as we uſe Children now; amuſed them with Fables and ſtrange Stories, and lead them which way they would, by complying with their Superſtition; to which purpoſe they took care the Doctrines they taught the People, ſhould be abſurd enough, and well adjuſted to the Lowneſs of their Underſtandings. This was really the caſe, and no better; for the Fabulous Age of the World was the time when theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Religions were firſt invented, and their Poets were the Authors of them; of which the Eldeſt either never wrote, or at leaſt nothing of their genuine Writings is now left: but of the Poets which do remain, we find always the oldeſt, as had in greateſt Veneration, ſo be ſure moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>The World in the mean time was like to thrive and grow in Underſtanding, under the Influence of ſuch Teachers, and in embracing Schemes of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103395:9"/>Religion formed in ſuch Times, Times of which we know nothing certainly beſides their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Yet Conſiderations of State, Management of deſigning Men, and the Intereſt that a great many had in them, kept theſe Superſtitions up in after-times; the bulk of the People being as ignorant as ever, and ſtill believing whatever they were taught. There were, no doubt, ſome wiſe and honeſt Men, who ſaw the Abſurdity of theſe things, and would have declaimed ſooner and more loudly againſt them, but were deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, 'tis likely, from the Attempt, partly by the Danger they might bring upon themſelves, and partly thro' a very right Opinion they had, that Religion was neceſſary for Society; and that tho' the eſtabliſh't one were very faulty, there might be more inconvenience in labouring a Change; eſpecially ſince they could not be ſure what Religion was true, to bring in the room of it, or indeed whether any were ſo: beſides it may be they thought, that in that State of things Prejudices were neceſſary to make the People have any notion of Religion; and therefore if they were once removed, the People, who are always ready to run into extremes, and if once unhinged, are very hard to be ſettled again, if they had ſhaken off the Religion they were bred in, would then perhaps take up with none at all. Some ſuch Thoughts probably kept in the Wiſer Heathens from expoſing the Folly and Inconſiſtency of the Religions then in uſe, who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103395:9"/>could eaſily have framed more rational Schemes, but were not ſure they could find out the True one; and therefore were content to ſit down by thoſe they had, and make the beſt Senſe of them they could.</p>
            <p>In time indeed they ventured, many of them, to refine a little, and by degrees endeavoured to explain away what was moſt apparently Abſurd; but this did not ſatisfie ſome, who being Men of more Heat and leſs Diſcretion, were for going faſter, and thinking they knew more than all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, could not keep in the mighty Secret any longer. The Credulity, implicite Belief and Bigotry the World had been ſo long under, about things they had ſcarce any notion at all of, made them run now into the other Extreme; and ſo firſt <hi>Scepticiſm</hi> and then downright <hi>Atheiſm</hi> became the Learning and Wiſdom of the World. Theſe Men having found the World was miſtaken in many things, began now to doubt of every thing, they began to queſtion the Being of any God at all; and having ſhewn with Reaſon enough on their ſide the folly and weakneſs of the common Opinions, as they were then corrupted, 'twas ſo hard to ſee the little Truth that lay under them, that without Diſtinction they threw them all away; and ſetting up for themſelves, entertained about almoſt all things new Opinions of their own, very different from what had been hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but not leſs Extravagant. And thus by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103395:10"/>different ways they came to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to the ſame end, and left the World in as ill a Condition as they found it, or rather made things worſe; for perhaps 'tis better to act upon wrong Principles, than none at all; for then Men may be govern'd by thoſe that are wiſer than themſelves, whereas the Men of no Principles can be govern'd neither by themſelves nor others.</p>
            <p>Some of the main Points about which the World, when they began to think freely, were employed, were theſe; Firſt, They were much in the dark, whether there were ſuch a thing as an Eternal Intelligent Being or not; if there were, wherein his Nature conſiſted, and what were his chief Attributes; and if there were one ſuch Being, who was infinitely Wiſe and Good, whether there were not an Evil one Equal in Power to him; without which they could not account for the Origine of Evil, which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways one great Difficulty. Next, if there were One Eternal Mind, and but One, which we call GOD, whether he made the World or not; if he did, whether he only put things into that Frame and Order they are now in, or whether he made the things themſelves out of Nothing; If the former, for the latter was an Opinion that all their Philoſophy was not able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, whether this GOD were any other than the Soul of the World, animating the vaſt Maſs of Matter, after the ſame manner as the Soul of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103395:10"/>Man actuates his little World. Again, if GOD were a Being intirely diſtinct from the Univerſe, with which many of them confounded him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did at all intereſt himſelf in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the World, after he had made it; that is, whether there were any Providence or not, whether his Happineſs did not conſiſt in perpetual Eaſe and Reſt, and conſequently whether any Care or Thought of Buſineſs were not inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with it; or if he did meddle and concern himſelf with the Government of Things, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Care were not confin'd within certain Bounds, in looking after the great Springs and Wheels of the Machine, while the Sublunary things and this lower World were quite neglected; or if he took care of them too, whether this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the Inſenſible and Vegetable part only, or to the Senſible and Rational; if to them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he governed the Minds and Actions of Men, or only their involuntary Motions; if their Minds and Thoughts and Actions, whether by a chain of Cauſes link'd together in a perpetual and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Order, or only by a Concurrence with their own free voluntary Motions; if the latter, whether Men were by that rendred capable of Moral Good and Moral Evil; if capable, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were actually accountable to GOD for what they do; which ſuppoſes that there are fixt and unalterable Rules or Good and Evil, that theſe Rules are the Will of GOD, that he has declared this Will of his to Man; if ſo, what
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103395:11"/>and how many are theſe Rules; when and where Revealed; are they all of Perpetual and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Obligation or not; if ſome only, which are they; what Puniſhments are annext to the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them; when to be inflicted, in this Life or another; if in another, the Soul muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and immaterial, and the Man muſt live again; beſides many other Difficulties, which muſt be determined, before we can know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man be actually accountable to GOD for what he does.</p>
            <p>Theſe, all theſe are Queſtions of great Importance, and ſuch as the wiſeſt Heathens could come to no certain Concluſions about: Some of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by an extraordinary Goodneſs of Mind have hit upon Noble Thoughts, and very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Truth; but when well examined, they appear to be, what themſelves could rather wiſh to be true, than be at all ſure they were ſo. I ſhall give but one Inſtance of this, and that is in that excellent Diſcourſe of <hi>Socrates</hi> before his Death; in which there are ſtrange and ſurprizing Strokes of Truth, about the Immortality of the Soul, and the Rewards and Puniſhments of another Life. Who can without pity ſee the weak Efforts of the beſt Reaſon? who can forbear wiſhing him Succeſs, or not be ſorry, extremely ſorry at his Diſappointment, who has ſuch noble Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in view; but is utterly at a loſs, by what certain Steps to get at them? One ſees him
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103395:11"/>through all along that piece, very earneſt in the ſearch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and purſuit of Truth; he ſometimes takes ſuch true Steps, and purſues ſo cloſely, that one can't help thinking every minute, the next will be the laſt, he ſeems ſo very near it; and then loſes his Scent a while, and then comes on again; which gives the Reader a very melancholy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, who can't but be in ſome ſort diſappointed himſelf, every time he ſees He is. The Diſcourſe thro'out muſt be own'd to be at firſt Sight very Beautiful; but if one view the Picture nicely, examine the ſeveral Parts of it, the Proportions and Reaſons on which they are built, the whole will appear ſuch a ſtrange mixture of Truth and Error, full of ſuch inconcluſive Arguments, ſo like Dreaming of ſome Fairy Land, that one can't but wonder how it could come from the Hand of ſo great a Maſter, or be thought a finiſht Piece by thoſe that heard it. In truth, under all the Good-will he diſcovers for ſo good a Cauſe, one can't but obſerve with how much Diffidence himſelf ſpeaks of it; much leſs can any body elſe be convinc'd by what he ſays, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſuch as come prepar'd to believe before they hear, and can take up with Concluſions firſt, and then look out for Premiſes, by which they may ſeem to others to have come to them.</p>
            <p>So great was the Blindneſs and Ignorance the World was under about things of the greateſt moment; I might proceed to ſhew that their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103395:12"/>Works alſo were Works of Darkneſs; that their Manners, generally ſpeaking, were as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt as their Opinions; but the cloſe Conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion there is between Religion and Morality makes this leſs neceſſary, nor have I time for it, if I would. How far this Corruption was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable and invincible, I will not now diſpute: Thus much is certain, the World either had no means to remove it, or at leaſt did not know how to uſe them, and conſequently would never have remov'd it, had not the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Time been reveal'd to them. In Him <hi>the People that walked in Darkneſs, have ſeen a great Light: they that dwell in the Land of the Shadow of Death, upon them hath the Light ſhined.</hi> 'Twas He diſpell'd theſe clouds which had ſo long hung over the Earth; He enlightned the World after this long and univerſal Dark, this black eternal Night.</p>
            <p>Wherein this Enlightning the World conſiſted, was the Second thing I propos'd to ſpeak to; which I ſhall do very briefly.</p>
            <p>It conſiſted then in introducing a new State of things, a State in all its parts oppoſite to that I have been deſcribing; in teaching the World all That is neceſſary for them to know of Divine things, of the Nature of GOD, and of Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; in giving us juſt and true Notions of the Divine Providence, of his Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103395:12"/> in governing the World; in laying down excellent Rules of Living well, and teaching us the true nature of Moral Good and Evil; and laſtly, in giving us a reaſonable Worſhip, worthy of Man, and in ſome ſort worthy his Creator.</p>
            <p>Now the World is no longer at a loſs to know what GOD is, what he Requires of us, and how he will be Served; now we have a certain Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our Duty, we have fixt unalterable Rules to go by; we depend now no longer on our own Reaſon, or the Authority of others; we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the higheſt Reaſon of the beſt Being, by the divine and infallible Guidance of the Son of GOD. Before, the World muſt either have follow'd the Dictates of ſome great Law-giver, or found out the Rules of their Duty for themſelves. As to the former, no Man ever had or could have an Authority to preſcribe to the reſt of the World, nor was it ſafe he ſhould, as appears from the great Imperfections, that are to be met with in the beſt <hi>Syſtemes</hi> of Human Laws: nor could they find out the Meaſure of their Duty them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for that requires vaſt Abilities, capable of drawing a very long Chain of Conſequences from a very few Principles; and therefore, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, yet is it what much the greateſt part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind have neither Capacity nor Opportunity for.</p>
            <p>But this is but a part only of what our Saviour has done for us; to all this he has added great and precious Promiſes, to invite us to our Duty, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103395:13"/>proportionable Threats to deter us from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: and that nothing might be wanting to compleat this great Redemption he hath wrought for us, that no one might complain he had not all due Aſſiſtance to enable him to do what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him, he hath graciouſly promiſed his holy Spirit to all them that call upon him.</p>
            <p>O! how thankful ought we all to be for this great Goodneſs of GOD to us, how careful not to undervalue it, as ſome do, who by a ſtrange Ingratitude, becauſe GOD hath ſuffered them to enjoy the Light, conclude there was no Darkneſs, and that the World would have been ſufficiently enlightned, tho' GOD had done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of all this for them. They deny the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Revelation, and bring down the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blime Perfection of the Chriſtian Religion to that which they call Natural: They can now prove to you from that all the Truths delivered in the Goſpel, and argue againſt Revealed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, from that very Light it furniſhes them with: And ſo in truth beg the Queſtion, while to prove they don't ſtand in need of Revelation, they produce as the Effect of their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſiſted Reaſon what was really borrow'd from it. They diſtinguiſh not between Reaſon with, and without the helps the Scriptures give it; which yet are very different things, as different as it is to find out a thing, and aſſent to it when it is found out: a Man may as well ſay, he can move
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103395:13"/>as regularly in the Dark as in the Light, becauſe he hath in both the Faculty of Moving; as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend he could reaſon as well without the Goſpel, as he can under it, becauſe he would have the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Reaſoning then as well as now. Could theſe Men poſſibly efface the early Notices they receiv'd from Revelation, they would ſoon think more meanly of themſelves, and ſee how ſmall Advances we ſhould make, if GOD in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure had ſtill left us to our ſelves: or, if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their great Opinion of themſelves, or the real Difficulty of the thing hinder them from judging of the Strength, or rather Weakneſs of their own Reaſon, in caſe it were diveſted of the helps they have from Revelation, a little Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will ſerve the turn: let them look back into the firſt Hiſtories of the earlieſt Times, let them read the beſt Diſcourſes of the ableſt Men, Men no way inferiour to them in Natural Abilities, Men of greater Induſtry, cloſer Thought and more Virtue; and then they will be eaſily convinc'd, unleſs they are reſolved not to ſee, how few Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions we are able to come to of our ſelves about Divine Matters, about GOD, Religion, Liberty, Morality, a future Judgment and Immortality.</p>
            <p>There is great reaſon to think theſe Men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for Natural Religion, not for its own ſake, but to pull down that which is revealed; and were that once done, they would deal eaſily enough with this, and ſo get to their beloved
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103395:14"/>Concluſion, That there is no Religion at all: They would then be very ingenious in ſhewing the Faults and Imperfections of what they now ſo much cry up, and would with Triumph prove, That they who have thrown off Revealed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, cannot reaſonably adhere to it; ſince the Difficulties againſt one, many of them at leaſt, lie equally againſt the other, if one be abſurd and too hard to be believed, ſo is the other, and no one, who can take up with the Principles of Natural Religion, can find it difficult to embrace the Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>But we have not ſo learned <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we ſee and know the great Things he hath done for us, that he is the true Light, and that the World was in Darkneſs before he came: He is the great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorer and Deliverer of Mankind from that Blindneſs and Ignorance the Degeneracy of their Nature had brought them under; 'twas He that formed anew, as it were, this Part of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and gave again to Man an underſtanding Heart; He ſtampt again upon him the Image of his Maker, that Image, on which the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Man over the reſt of the Creation was at firſt founded: which Preheminence before 'twas hard to ſee a reaſon for, he differed ſo very little from the Beaſts that periſh, but now hath GOD exalted him for ever, he hath once more made him a little lower than the Angels, he hath crowned him with Honour and Immortality,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103395:14"/>which is again brought to light by the Goſpel of his Son. <hi>This is the Lord's doing, and is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous in our Eyes;</hi> for this ſhould every Mouth be full of Thankſgiving, and every Tongue tell forth his Praiſe. 'Tis as impoſſible to have a Senſe of theſe Favours, and not be thankful for them, as 'tis for thoſe to be thankful, who have no Senſe of them.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, 'tis not enough to thank GOD on this wiſe: The Natural Conſequence of what he has done for us, is to deny Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and worldly Luſts, to have no Fellowſhip with the Unfruitful Works of Darkneſs, but to walk as Children of the Light and of the Day. The times of Darkneſs were times of Ignorance, and therefore GOD winked at them; but now ſince the Light of the Goſpel is ſhed abroad, he commands all Men every where to repent. Our Duty riſes in proportion to the Means GOD has furniſhed us with for the Performance of it; this every body is ſenſible of, this makes wicked Men ſo naturally plead Ignorance, this makes Men ſhut their Eyes ſo hard againſt the Light of the Goſpel, as being conſcious they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe, if the Light really ſhines upon them, and they ſee it does ſo, and yet ſtill work the Works of Darkneſs. Now if this be ſo, if our Duty increaſes as the Light does that is given us to work by, then are they under the greateſt Obligations, who enjoy moſt of this Light: And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103395:15"/> therefore as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Diſpenſation obliged them to a greater Perfection and Holineſs than what the Heathen World knew, ſo does <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> obliges us to a greater than either. We are taught that <hi>except our Righteouſneſs exceed the Righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, we ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the ſame Argument a greater Degree of Piety, Charity, and other Virtues will be required of ſome parts of the Chriſtian World above others, in as much as they enjoy greater Light, purer and leſs corrupted by Superſtition, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the remains of ancient Heatheniſm. This is the caſe of the Reformed Churches, in compariſon not only of the <hi>Roman,</hi> but of any other Chriſtian Church now in being: And if all the Reformed Churches enjoy not an equal Light, we have no reaſon to think any of them on this account more happy than our own. And indeed we are apt enough to own this, and pleaſe our ſelves with the thoughts of being of ſo pure a Church, where we have the Word of GOD conſtantly read and preached to us, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Sacraments, and daily Prayers: We are bred up to a rational and intelligible Devotion, we want neither the Subſtance nor Form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, we are taught to ſerve GOD with the pureſt Worſhip, and in the moſt decent Manner. But 'tis ſtrange to ſee Men cry up this Church,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103395:15"/> and value themſelves for being Members of it, and yet not ſee at the ſame time, how much more they have on this account to anſwer for; how by this means the great Plea of not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or not being taught their Duty is wholy taken from them.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not ſtop here; the Gradation from Heatheniſm to Judaiſm, and from thence to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity in general, then to the Reformed parts of it, and laſt of all to our own Church, this Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation muſt ſtill be carried one ſtep higher, from our Church to the Eyes of it the Univerſities. Here we meet with greater, much greater means of knowing and doing our Duty, than any other Place any where affords. And who does not ſee the Conſequence of this? were a Man who had never ſeen or heard of ſuch a Place as this before, for the firſt time made acquainted with the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and Deſign of it, the Laws we are govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by, the Care and Diſcipline and Method of inſtruction, and laſtly the great and good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples we live under; how would he long after the Original of ſo fair a Picture, how deſirous would he be to ſee this Beauty of our Earth? He would expect Learning to run down among us like a Stream, and Righteouſneſs like a Flood; he would expect to meet every where with bright and ſhining Inſtances of Piety and Holineſs, of Induſtry and Temperance, of Charity, Patience and Humility; in ſhort; ſomething far beyond the Improvements the reſt of the World are capable of.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:103395:16"/>
            <p>But I need not ſuppoſe what Thoughts a Man would have, who never ſaw any thing of a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity beyond the Scheme and Model of it; we are pretty well convinced, that this is what the World expects of us: for if they did not look for ſomething very perfect, they would think our Imperfections a great deal leſs, than we find they are apt to do. Which ſhould be an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Argument to us to walk worthy of the Light we have; for our Light is not like the Pillar that led the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old, a Light to them it was to guide, and Dark to all beſides; as we have this Light, ſo every body ſees we have it, and from thence are ready to take all advantages againſt us. I think we may without great Partiality to our ſelves ſay, We are not fairly dealt with in this matter; Envy and Ill-nature and a Spirit of Phanaticiſm, both as to the Civil and Religious State, have certainly a great ſhare in the loud Complaints againſt us; and they that rail at us for being no better, are many of them really ſorry, we are no worſe. Men who deſign to deſtroy all Principles of Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, can't with patience ſee thoſe Places flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, which are ſo directy oppoſite to ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, whoſe very End is to inſtill true Notions of theſe things, and root out all deſtructive Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions whatſoever. Which makes <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Deiſts</hi> neceſſarily Enemies to our very Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for Theſe are the Banks that keep out their pernicious Doctrines from breaking in upon the Nation. Not that theſe are all the Enemies we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103395:16"/> have; a little Truth mixed with a great deal of Calumny, has made our Faults appear much greater than they are; by which means other and better Men have been unhappily influenced to the Prejudice of theſe Places.</p>
            <p>But how unjuſt ſoever theſe Complaints are, we may make a right uſe of them, by mending what ever is amiſs, by walking more circumſpectly, and giving no Occaſion to the Adverſary. 'Tis the Fate of Perſons and Places that are Eminent; the more they are ſo, the more they are expos'd to publick View, and conſequently Cenſure; for many, a great many take a View of them, not to admire their Beauty or Excellency, but to find ſome Fault with them, and then are moſt diſappointed when they find feweſt. And as this is generally one of the Diſadvantages of a high Station, ſo it is in a peculiar manner, and for particular reaſons, the Fortune or rather Fate of thoſe Illuſtrious Bodies the Univerſities.</p>
            <p>But to return from this Digreſſion, which a juſt Senſe of the Light we live under, the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations it laies on us, and the Reſtleſneſs of our Enemies has led me to; where much is given, much is required, and in return of great Favours, great Duties become due from us; and if we would be the better for the Light that is come into the World, we muſt endeavour to deſerve it; we can have no benefit in the bright Shining of the Goſpel, unleſs we renounce the hidden
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103395:17"/>Pleaſures of the Night. GOD did not give us this Light to glory in our Shame, and ſhew that we can be wicked ſtill, that we can abuſe his Grace, and dare produce thoſe Monſters into open Day, which before were ſhrowded under the cover of the Dark. No, what was then excuſable, is now no longer ſo; to prefer the abſurd Pleaſures of Sin before the Beauty and Comelineſs of Virtue, when our Eyes are open, and in the day, this is very unnatural and unpardonable, this proves we want common Senſe as well as common Gratitude, this can't but be highly provoking to Almighty GOD, who beſtow'd theſe Favours on us to quite other Purpoſes. Let us not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any longer diſtinguiſh our time as Chriſtians into Light and Darkneſs, and think we have the night ſtill left to revel in: the Darkneſs now will not cover us, <hi>the Darkneſs is no Darkneſs to us, the Light is as clear as the Day, the Darkneſs and Light to us are both alike.</hi> For ſince the Sun of Righteouſneſs is riſen, ſince He that was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning Light, Eternal Light, is come down among us and become the Light of Men; to this new State agrees the Deſcription St. <hi>John</hi> gives us of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with which I ſhall conclude. <hi>The City had no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it; for the Glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the Light thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103395:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
